<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon briefly comparing the estate of King Salomon and his subiectes togither with the condition of Queene Elizabeth and her people preached in Sainct Maries in Oxford the 17. of Nouember, and now printed with some small alteration, by Iohn Prime, 1585</title>
            <author>Prime, John, 1550-1596.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1585</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10113</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20371</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115247</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850466</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850466</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15673</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10113)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15673)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 971:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon briefly comparing the estate of King Salomon and his subiectes togither with the condition of Queene Elizabeth and her people preached in Sainct Maries in Oxford the 17. of Nouember, and now printed with some small alteration, by Iohn Prime, 1585</title>
                  <author>Prime, John, 1550-1596.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ioseph Barnes printer to the Vniuersitie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1585.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>In another edition (STC 20371.5) line 3 of title has: subiects.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Elizabeth --  I, --  Queen of England, 1533-1603 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15673:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15673:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON BRIEF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY COMPARING THE E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STATE OF KING SALOMON AND his Subiectes togither with the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Queene ELIZABETH and her people.</p>
            <p>PREACHED IN SAINCT <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in Oxford the</hi> 17. <hi>of Nouember, and now printed with ſome ſmall alteration, by</hi> IOHN PRIME, 1585.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>IMPRINTED AT OXFORD by <hi>Ioſeph Barnes</hi> Printer to the Vniuerſitie. 1585.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15673:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15673:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE CHRISTIAN</hi> Reader Grace and Peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>RESENT occaſion (gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Reader) moueth me to preſent thee with this litle Sermon, lately prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched &amp; earneſtly reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted at my hands. Once printing doeth eaſe the often copying out. Verily therein is no great matter of ſuch moment, but only a deſire to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and ſtir vp ſome duetifull cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the mindes of the hearers in theſe laſt and vnthankefull dayes.</p>
            <p>And ſoothly, I was the leſſe carefull to perfourm many proofes either of the Princes ſacred authoritie or happie go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment in the execution and fruites thereof, being priuie afore-hand to the printing of M. D. <hi>Bilſons</hi> verie learned and like careful booke in theſe reſpects, euen now comming foorth, by way of thorough &amp; perfit anſwere to turbulent wits and troubleſome heades, and vaine
<pb facs="tcp:15673:3"/>
               <hi>defenders of falſly ſo called Catholiques a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the neceſſary and mercifull execution of due Iuſtice and her Maieſties Lawes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And herein (good Reader) my verie hart reioyceth that the long barenneſſe of one and the ſame College at length with much adoe firſt hath brought forth him enabled to incounter with the beſt of our olde deceiued predeceſſours, to witte: D. <hi>Cole,</hi> D. <hi>Harpsfield,</hi> D. <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> D. <hi>Sanders, Dorman, Raſtall,</hi> D. <hi>Stapleton, Points, Marſhall, Fouler, Hide, William Rainoldes</hi> and the reſt. God of his goodnes increaſe our knowledge zeal and diſcretion, to the diſcharge of our dueties vnto the ful.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.</note>
               <hi>Pharao non dimittet niſi in manu valida:</hi> Poperie is not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by ſilence, ignorance and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. And know you my brethren of greater ability &amp; gifts (who euer you be) it is a certaine experienced truth; Papiſts neuer flocke togither, neuer mutter Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dod and Spaniſh in corners, neuer vent &amp; ſparſe abroad lies &amp; fables at ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry meetings, neuer write, crake &amp; vaunt
<pb facs="tcp:15673:3"/>ſo faſt, but as croking toades againſt a ſtorme. God make vs wiſe to diſcern who be who, and ready preſt alwayes to diuert their ſpite, &amp; defend his truth. Remember that word: <hi>Negotiamim,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 13.</note>
               <hi>donec veniam.</hi> Hide not your talents, omit not oportunities, occupie till I come. Fare you well in Chriſt Ieſu.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>New Colledge in Oxford <date>27. Nouemb. 1585.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:15673:4"/>
            <head>1. KINGS 10.9. Bleſſed be the Lord thy God, which loued thee, to ſet thee on the throne of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> becauſe he loued <hi>Iſrael</hi> for euer, and made thee King to doe equitie and righteouſneſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words, ſome yeares<note n="*" place="margin">1574.</note> ſince (as ſome of you may remember) vppon this yearelie and happie occaſion were moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly, largely, and effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuallie debated with you. In reſuming the ſame againe, my purpoſe is not to venture flight with the Eagle, or to run with the Gyant, or any way to compare with that excellent man. Onelie, for good reaſons mouing me there-unto, I haue rather choſen to ſowe in a ground readie plowed vp to my hand, than to breake vppe a newe at mine owne choice.</p>
            <p>Without more adoe, or farther im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent
<pb facs="tcp:15673:4"/>prefacing, theſe woordes and the whole ſtorie of the Queene of <hi>Saba</hi> is not only recorded<note n="*" place="margin">1. King. 10</note> here, but alſo word for woorde repeated againe in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter booke of <hi>Chronicles,</hi> as a matter woorthy all memorie and admiration.<note place="margin">2. Chron. 9.</note> For, that a woman and ſhee a Queene, and (as our Sauiour noteth) from the fartheſt partes of the earth,<note place="margin">Mat. 12.45</note> onelie moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with the fame of a wiſe man, ſhould come ſo readilie to learne wiſedome, is more than ſtraunge, &amp; deſerueth euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting praiſe with all poſteritie in ages ſucceeding, and ſhee ſhall riſe at the laſt day of doome and iudgement to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of the maruelous ſloth of ſome whole generations. Some other,<note place="margin">Luc. 11.31.</note> her like, would haue dealt after a diuerſe and a diſlike ſort, as for example, reaſoning thus: I am a woman, by nature weake and can not; a Queene, and neede not; of ſoueraigne eſtate and it were vnſeeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to leaue my people at random and to uenture at auentures &amp; to trauell abroad. The way is long and tedious: the iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
<pb facs="tcp:15673:5"/>daungerous, full of cruell beaſtes, and of men woorſe than beaſtes: the fame is but a report, and reportes are not alwaies true. But ſhee fore-caſteth none of all theſe doubts and inconueniences, neither the vncertainty of the euent, nor perill of the way, nor tediouſneſſe of the iourney, nor dignity of her perſon, nor infirmitie of her ſexe. She, as a faire type, and a timely firſt-fruite of the gentils, preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth herſelf among the people of GOD, preferring the aduenture for wiſedome, more,<note place="margin">Prou. 3.15.</note> than for ſiluer, gold, or what euer thing elſe of richeſt price. And beeing nowe come to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> conferreth at large with <hi>Salomon</hi> himſelfe, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth ſpeciall aunſwere in euery thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue expectation. After a while, ſhe ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueieth his buildinges, and taketh parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular viewe of his whole houſe and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, and when ſhee had conſidered all; the order of his realme, the array of his ſeruiters, the manner of his waiters, their attire, their diet, their bleſſed roume and place whereby they enioyed the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
<pb facs="tcp:15673:5"/>preſence of ſo woonderfullie wiſe a Prince, that could aunſwere to euery her queſtion, demaund, and motiue that ſhee could make, ſhe was all amazed, and her ſpirite was taken from her. And com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to herſelfe againe, ſhe breaketh forth no doubt, by the ſpirite of God into the woordes of my text:
<q>Bleſſed be the Lord, thy God which loued thee &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>A bleſſed God and a louing,
a bleſſed Prince, and
a bleſſed people beloued of God.</p>
            <p>A bleſſed God, to be praiſed and bleſſed for euer (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh) <hi>Amen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.25. &amp; 9.5.</note> But wherewith this Queene beginneth, namely, with the praiſe and bleſſing of God, God willing, we meane to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace all, and end the whole. In the meane while, conſider wee apart Gods bleſſings,
<list>
                  <item>1 vpon <hi>Salomom,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>2 vpon <hi>Salomons</hi> ſubiects.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1 Salomons</hi> bleſſing, and louely eſtate is therefore termed ſo and ſo pronounced
<pb facs="tcp:15673:6"/>here becauſe god placed him in the throne of regiment amongſt his people. And in truth, to be a plant in the Lordes orchard, to bee the woorkmanſhippe of his owne hands, toward the toppe, or in the midle, or neere the foundation, or where-about ſo-euer in the frame of his building, euen to bee the pooreſt doore-keeper in all his houſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.10.</note> is no ſmall benefit, or common bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: yet is this more properly his doing, and hee alone chiefly planteth and placeth all that are allotted to chiefeſt roumes. The Sunne placeth not it ſelfe aboue the Moone and ſtarres: The head ſetteth not it ſelfe vpon the ſhoulders: By<note n="*" place="margin">Prou. 8.15</note> me (ſaith the wiſedome of God) Kings raigne: as if it were ſaide, if by others, as it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained in the Prophet <hi>Oſce,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Oſe. 8.4.</note> then not by me, and therefore by me alone (ſaith the wiſedom of God) Kings raigne: that is, they beare their ſcepters and weare their ſwordes and ſit in their thrones, <hi>BY ME</hi> they raigne.</p>
            <p>And, great reaſon wee thus iudge of Soueraigne authoritie. All thinges in the
<pb facs="tcp:15673:6"/>world: the leaſt, the vileſt, the leaſt of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; the leafe of a flower, the fall of a ſparowe, the feather of a bird, the foode of rauens, the fodder of oxen, the briſſell of a hogge (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh,) the teares of our eies, and colour of our haire come all within the ſpan and compaſſe of God almighties power-full doing, and particular direction. Nowe, he that careth for litle thinges, is he careleſſe of the greateſt? He that careth for the haire, he can not but care for the body: and hee that careth for the bodie, careth for the head; and he that reſpecteth the bodie, the head, the haire, the whole, the parts, great and leſſe, principall and excrementall of priuate men, without all queſtion regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth much more the bodie politike and the heade of the common-wealth.<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1. 1. Pet. 2.13.</note>
               <hi>All au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie is of God,</hi> and therefore kinglie moſt of all, euen as all the waters iſhue from the Ocean, but more immediatlie the great riuers.</p>
            <p>This ſpeach were vtterly needleſſe, were wee not fallen into the waining of
<pb facs="tcp:15673:7"/>the world,<note place="margin">Iude 8.</note> wherein S. <hi>Iudes</hi> reprehenſion may iuſtly take place: when men are not onely deſpiſers of gouernours, as <hi>Shimei</hi> was of <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.5</note> but euill ſpeakers and miſconſterers of authoitrie it ſelfe and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne gouernment in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. <hi>Treaſon againſt the Prince is no ſinne againſt God, ſaith Euerard Hance,</hi> as you may reade in the wiſe and <hi>True re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Arrainment and execution of the Popiſh Traitor.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euerard Hance, <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias</hi> Ducket</note>
            </p>
            <p>Our preſent ſtorie, of the enthronizing of <hi>Salomon</hi> informeth vs better, &amp; teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs a contrary leſſon, and ſheweth plainly, whence princely gouernment is deriues and doth depend. I know, <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabe Salomons</hi> mother, <hi>Dauid</hi> his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet, <hi>Zadock</hi> the Prieſt, were all for <hi>Salomon.</hi> But <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doniah</hi> was the elder brother, and <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> the yonger; <hi>Abiathar</hi> the high prieſt annointed <hi>Adoniah,</hi> and not <hi>Salomon; Salomons</hi> mother was a blemiſhed wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and <hi>Adoniah</hi> was in a kinde of real poſſeſſion of the kingdom, and what hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb facs="tcp:15673:7"/>meanes can we imagine then could hinder him and them, and helpe <hi>Salomon</hi> to remedie all? <hi>Ioab</hi> a great man and a mightie for valour, cunning and courage, would venter limme &amp; life, and had ſet his reſt vppon the cauſe.</p>
            <p>Wherfore <hi>Bennaiah</hi> when he ſaw how the world went,<note place="margin">1. Reg. 1.36.</note> yet on the contrary ſide perceiuing how <hi>Dauid</hi> was reſolued that <hi>Salomon</hi> for al this ſhold ſucceed, wiſhed from his heart it might be ſo: <hi>So bee it,</hi> ſaid he, &amp; not contented therewith addeth after in few but effectual words, praying: <hi>The Lord God of the Lord my king ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie it.</hi> As if he ſhould haue ſaide, <hi>Berza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be, Zadocke, Nathan, and I,</hi> yea <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe would haue it ſo: but <hi>God</hi> ſay ſo <hi>to.</hi> For if God ſay no it can not be, but if he ſay ſo notwithſtanding all vnlikelihoods, if God ratified it, it ſhall ſtande, and muſt be ſo.</p>
            <p>A worthy and a wiſe and a true ſaying (and to conclude this matter) moſt agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the <hi>Pſalme:</hi> Promotion commeth neither from the Eaſt, nor the Weſt. No,<note place="margin">Pſal. 75.6.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:15673:8"/>my brethren nor from the north, nor ſouth. The Lord of Lordes and king of kinges and gouernour of all thinges, ruleth, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruleth al in al ſpecially al theſe caſes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment euen by his plenary power and at his owne and abſolute pleaſure: as hath beene vouched in generall and in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar is declared that his meere loue to Prince and people it was that placed <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> &amp; diſappointed <hi>Adoniah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in ſooth, is it ſuch a bleſſing ſo great a benefit proceeding all of loue to bee a king? Howe ſaith one, that the Princely cloke is lined all within with pinnes and pricking needles? An other that a crown is not worth the ſtouping for? A thirde, that, if profer were made neceſſarily to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept either preſent death, or the Princely Diademe, he would make willing choice rather to go ſtraitway to his graue, than any way to the chaire of eſtate. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe domeſtical examples touch neereſt, &amp; affect moſt, our ſoueraine &amp; careful queene the Lordes annointed ouer vs, in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to her councell and iudges, for
<pb facs="tcp:15673:8"/>a due conſideration ouer her people, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g other words euer to be reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred of their honors, hath theſe of her ſelfe: <hi>I care not for my ſelfe, my life is not deere vnto me: My care is for my people.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In. B. Iewels view of the Bull.</note>
               <hi>I pray god who euer ſucceedeth me, he as care full as I am. They, who might know what cares I beare, would not thinke it ſo great a ioy to weare the crowne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the booke of <hi>Iudges</hi> the ninth chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter there is a parable and a ſtorie to this purpoſe; read you the ſtory,<note place="margin">Iudges. 9.</note> I will touch onely the parable: In deede the ſweete figge tree, the pleaſant vine, the fatte oliue refuſed preferment, when it was offered. But (beloued) figtrees, vines and Oliues are geiſen and rare, &amp; grow not in euery ground. The ſcratching bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that is rife &amp; common in euery hedge, redily accepteth the offer, &amp; willed al the trees to come vnder his ſhadow without ſtraining curſie at the matter. Generally, <hi>Adams</hi> children, ſome more, ſome leſſe, &amp; almoſt al, haue ſome deſire to ride the horſe they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not manage.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.</note>
               <hi>Abſalo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> in this affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:15673:9"/>embezelleth the harts of the ſubiects from his own moſt louing father.<note place="margin">Heſter. 6.6.</note>
               <hi>Aman</hi> blown vp with this winde would needes ride the kingly horſe, and weare the Princely robe and ring, with ſound of trumpet &amp; procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation made in open ſight. <hi>Thus ſhall the man be honoured whom the king will honor.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyprian. de Ten. &amp; Ierunio.</note> Yea <hi>ambition</hi> (ſaith <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi>) <hi>ſleepeth</hi> (and lodgeth) <hi>in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of Prieſtes.</hi> No, no, <hi>Cyprian,</hi> lodge it may, but where it lodgeth it can not ſleepne maketh men wake when other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſleepe. Neither will I wander abroade for proafe hereof: It cauſed <hi>Yorke</hi> to ſtriue with <hi>Canterburie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cardinal Woolſey.</note> and <hi>Canterburie</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to ſtruggle with the king, and <hi>Yorke</hi> againe of later yeares it made to bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt and for the Pope: and laſtly to the end to be Pope himſelfe he would venter all <hi>England,</hi> as the Pope doth alwaies al Chriſtendome to maintaine his triple crowne. <hi>Philarchie</hi> luſt for honour, and loue of imperie troubled not onely ſome ſingle men,<note place="margin">Nazian. ad Procop.</note> but (as in <hi>Nazianzens</hi> time) whole councels were ſo ſea-ſick with this
<pb facs="tcp:15673:9"/>paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that <hi>Nazianzenes</hi> quiet nature was fully reſolued neuer to reſort to ſuch diſtem pered aſſemblies. But if it be thus in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſt hood, much worſe it can not chooſe but be in their minds, whoſe life is a worldly glory &amp; whoſe only deſire is to be aloft, to be the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narks, if it bee but of a mole-hill: and yet ſome whole dominions are to litle for ſome, &amp; ſometimes meaner men of lower lot can dreame euen <hi>Ioſephs</hi> dreame,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 37.</note> but not with <hi>Ioſephes</hi> ſpirite: that al the ſheaues of the field muſt ſtoupe to their ſheaue, that the ſun moon and ſtarres, the Queene, Nobles and realme muſt bowe &amp; bend before a ſtinking ſnuf, a <hi>Stukeley,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thomas Stukeley.</note> a faithleſſe perſon &amp; periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red beaſt, &amp; yet the beſt inſtrument of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fathers pride. But pride hath had hir de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued ruine. As <hi>Abſolons</hi> fancifal heade was hanged in his own lockes, and <hi>Haman</hi> on his own gallowes, ſo <hi>Stukeley</hi> &amp; <hi>Stuke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leis</hi> like haue had their iuſt deſerts, &amp; drank the wine of their own vintage.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all this, to vſe <hi>Hamans</hi> words to a truer ſenſe, moſt true it is: <hi>So &amp; ſo and in greater, truer, &amp; incomparably
<pb facs="tcp:15673:10"/>better ſort ſhal he be honored, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God will honor,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this moſt honorable calling of being a lawful prince to the end he be his own lieutena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,<note place="margin">2. Chro. 9.8.</note> to ſit in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> throne <hi>in his own ſtead,</hi> to be &amp; bear the image of his maieſty, to haue the credit of kingdoms, &amp; care of his people, to feed <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to guide <hi>Iacob,</hi> to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uern <hi>Iudah,</hi> to be a foſter-father &amp; a nurſing mother vnto his Church; to bee the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; angel of God, as the woman of <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuah</hi> ſaid to <hi>Dauid,</hi> to be the horſe &amp; chariot, the bones and ſtrength; to be the head, &amp; the eie of direction, for iuſtice, equity &amp; good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in a commonwealth. This is no ſmall prerogatiue or common priuilege. And in one word, this was <hi>Salomons</hi> caſe: &amp; was this no bleſſing?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> In the ſecond place conſider we the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing &amp; loue of God towarde <hi>Salomons</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects. As the wickedneſſe of the king bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the wrath of God vpon the whole realm <hi>Gen. 20.9.</hi> ſo when wiſe &amp; very wiſe men gouern, the gouermnent is ſtable, and they ſo gouerned are moſt happy. As when <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſhould build the temple, he cared litle
<pb facs="tcp:15673:10"/>for hey, for ſtraw, for vnte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pered morter, for vnſkilful workmen, he ſent for <hi>Hyera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uided (as <hi>Dauid</hi> his father had done before him) for the gold of <hi>Ophir,</hi> &amp; cedars of <hi>Liba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus:</hi> Euen ſo God in the edifice of his choſen peculiar people, for the greater benefite and beuty of the whole work, he chuſeth no <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal,</hi> no foole as <hi>Nabal</hi> was to be their ruſer, but <hi>Salomon</hi> the wiſeſt man that euer was. If the prince bee wiſe, the people be the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer; if he be bleſſed of God, they be moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py. <hi>Si caecus caeco praeierit:</hi> If the head be il, the members cannot proſper: if the blinde lead the blind, they both fal into the pit &amp; the pit is bottomleſſe: but if the eſe be ſound, the fiſh is ſweet. A good neighbour (as we ſay) is a great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity, a grations prince hath no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon to ſpeake of. A candle lighteth a houſe, the ſun the world: a wel is compete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for a few, it is the ſtream that caſeth the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie: one beame beareth an other, one peece of a bough feedeth another; it is the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is the roote that vpholdeth the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding &amp; cheriſheth the whole tree. Somway ſemblably in this caſe, <hi>Iſrael</hi> reaped mutual
<pb facs="tcp:15673:11"/>helpe ech of other, but the ſun, the generall light, the ſtreame, the foundation, the root of their bliſſe &amp; whole repoſe next &amp; imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly vnder God depended altogether and reſted moſt in hauing <hi>Salomon</hi> to be their prince. Vnder him, their peace and plenty was more than woonderfull, ſiluer was as common as ruble in the ſtreetes, and euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſate without any feare at ful eaſe vnder his vine. Were theſe no bleſſings? No dout the Lords bleſſings &amp; rare effects of his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular loue, wherein he bleſſed <hi>Salomon</hi> and by him them, powring the ointment on his head that it might deſcend &amp; be deriued to the reſt parts of the whole body of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. Not the pooreſt woman, but had acceſſe,<note place="margin">1. Kin. 3.17.</note> and inioyed her right, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the ſtrife for the liue child, and whoſe the deade ſhould be. So wiſe, ſo willing a prince was he, ſo happy a people were they, and (which was all in all) ſo louing a God was God vnto them both.</p>
            <p>And heere I pray you haue reſort your ſelues vnto, and view the ſtory as it lieth in the Bible, and you ſhal perceaue I haue but
<pb facs="tcp:15673:11"/>tripped ouer things. And nowe, becauſe I am deſired to bee ſhort, who neuer loued length, right worſhipful and deere countri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, looke wee homeward a litle, and as it were out of the looking glaſſe of this ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by way of reflexion I beſeech you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what bleſſings alſo on vs God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed, by what meanes they haue been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, &amp; what dutifulnes is due therefore. Flattery becommeth no place, but leſt of al the pulpit. Be it ſpoken to the praiſe of God for it is a truth, and you, who knowe anie thing and haue a true taſt of things, knowe I lie not; God hath bleſſed her maieſty with a wiſe, a wealthy, a peaceable, and a godlie raigne.</p>
            <p>THE time was, when <hi>Steuen Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diner</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> and <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celler</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> a wilier ſerpent than all his brethren, worſe than <hi>Abiathar,</hi> and as bad as <hi>Achitophel</hi> laied his complot to preuent her preferment, and in deede vpon vaine ſurmiſes without all proofe or legall caling to queſtion moſt wrongfully brought her Grace to that heauy and doleful plight,
<pb facs="tcp:15673:12"/>that for griefe of minde, and ſorow of heart ſhe heartily wiſhed rather to haue beene a poore milkmaid in <hi>Woodſtocke</hi> park than a Kinges daughter, and a Queenes ſiſter, and heire apparent to ſundrie Bealmes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Lorde William Howard &amp; the Lord Williams, &amp; ſome others could do no more than they could.</note>In al the world ſhe found no friend, no a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble friend, no firme hope or preſent help but in God alone, <hi>the ſure rock of her founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Only he that is mighty magnified her and tooke her from the priſon, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> from the ſtocks, and made her our Queene, and as it were a <hi>Martha</hi> to prouide for Chriſt in his members, and as a <hi>Marie</hi> to heare him in his miniſters, and as a verie <hi>Debora,</hi> to execute iuſtice, equitie and trueth in this Engliſh Nation. And hee, that preferred her at the firſt, preſerueth her ſtill, (and preſerue her euer.) But all this was, becauſe he had a tender, a fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and fatherly reſpect to her and our former troubles for euer more.</p>
            <p>Since her happy raign, ſome unhappy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (as what field hath not ſome blaſted eares?) haue ſought (&amp; if they will needes be traitors, long may they ſeek but all in vain)
<pb facs="tcp:15673:12"/>the ruine of the realme, and deſtruction of her perſon, but they haue not preuailed at al. The maſter of all miſrule <hi>Pius</hi> the fifth, &amp; his Bull which <hi>Harding</hi> and his felow pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, &amp; <hi>Felton</hi> affixed in her principal city, <hi>Moortons</hi> conſpiracy with <hi>Weſtmerland</hi> and his complices in the North, <hi>Daluies</hi> promiſed aide; the great and popular man with all his potent endeuours, rumors and vauntings of the Duke of <hi>Florence</hi> and <hi>Don</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> what haue they effected? haue they preuailed? In late times and very lately of greene memory, <hi>Mendoza</hi> his tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels and treacherous embaſſay: his and his caſting lots for our garments, <hi>Throgmor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> beadroll of recuſants, and kalender of Ingliſh helpe for the inuading of <hi>England, Ardens</hi> villanous deſire, <hi>Somerfieldes</hi> dagge, and <hi>Ap-harries</hi> dagger, as <hi>Stories</hi> axe in former times, haue miſſed their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked purpoſes all, and haue not preuailed. Forren enimies, home libellers and rebels mighty or weake, many or fewe, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile or raſh, ſecret or open, they haue vndone themſelues, againſt vs, our Queene and
<pb facs="tcp:15673:13"/>contrary they haue not preuailed.</p>
            <p>Herein it is not to be denied, her ſacred Maieſty &amp; her moſt honorable councell haue <hi>Argus</hi> eies (or rather to ſpeake in this place more religiouſly, &amp; leſſe profanely) In great meaſure, wiſe hearts haue they, as <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> had; her friends are many &amp; ſure, her no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles truſty, her ſeruants true, &amp; her ſubiects loyall, her people willing &amp; her realme no begger. Siluer is not as plenty, as ſtones in the ſtreetes, yet moſt men haue more plate now than their great grandfathers had peu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in elder age, &amp; for general munitions, the like ſtore of weapons, armour, ſhot, pouder, &amp; people were neuer comparable in her an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors dates, her nauy incomparably ſtrong &amp; the ſea about vs a maine defence. But, but (deere countrimen, &amp; chriſtians) as I tolde you the other day, except God had watched &amp; warded &amp; kept our citie, except he had held his holy hand ouer vs, except he had riſen vp like a Giant, &amp; plesaded his, her &amp; our cauſe againſt our, her, &amp; his mortall foes, except he had bard our gates, &amp; bared his arme and ſtretched it foorth for our defence (<hi>Sanders</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:15673:13"/>warring; <hi>Alen</hi> libelling; the Ieſuits finely lying, ſophiſtically iugling, &amp; doubtfully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering; the Pope curſing; the <hi>Guiſe</hi> prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing; the Spaniard vndermining, <hi>Ireland</hi> &amp; the North rebelling, &amp; pioners ſtill wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king) what had bin come of this litle realm?</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding, brethren, bee of good cheere, lift vp your heades, your hands and hearts; lift vp your heades and bee of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, your handes to heauen &amp; your hearts to God, the God and horne of our ſaluation, the Lord of hoſts. The horſe of <hi>Egypt</hi> is fleſh &amp; not ſpirit, their men but men &amp; not God. The blaſt of a horne,<note place="margin">Ioſua. 6. Iudges. 7.</note> the blaze &amp; flaſh of a broken lamp, litle things in the eies of the world and leſſe in their own conceit haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerturned cities, conquered countries, and vanquiſhed giants when God ſo would. And one woman by the helpe of him, in whom ſhe truſteth, euen <hi>ELIZABETH</hi> by the grace of God our gracious Queene is and ſhalbe, and ſhalbe reputed for euer, the terror of her foes, the comfort of her friends, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of <hi>England,</hi> the Iewel of the world, and diamond of chriſtendom. Euen ſo <hi>(O Lord)</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:15673:14"/>becauſe of perfit loue thou haſt loued her ſo.</p>
            <p>In the meane time vnnaturally minded men, traitors to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> &amp; enimies to <hi>Sio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> hauing euill will to both commonwealth &amp; church of ours, &amp; thinking it beſt fiſhing whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the water is trobled moſt, ban &amp; curſe, raue &amp; take on like mad men, or loſing mates &amp; loſt companions, not ſeeing ſo much as <hi>Balaam</hi> that ſawe leſſe than his Aſſe, and yet ſaw thus much and ſayd accordingly, <hi>that for a houſe ful of gold he could not curſe where God did bleſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But is there no remedy? can no muſicke aſſuage theſe paſſions? Will <hi>Ephraim</hi> bee wilfull? Wil <hi>Iſraell</hi> truſt to a reed? can Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts imagine that ſtrangers will doe them good? and deeme they that God wil proſper a curſing generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? And what if their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries (which god auert) might take effect? * he,<note place="margin">Oſe. 8.7</note> that ſoweth a wind, ſhall he not reape a whirle-wind? do they remember, or haue they forgotten, or haue they not reade cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Melunes</hi> moſt memorable counſel to our Engliſh nobles?<note place="margin">Mat. Pariſ. Radolph Niger. <hi>cap.</hi> 47.</note> who, (after that the barons of this realme, miſſed by fancy of their own,
<pb facs="tcp:15673:14"/>and faction of the Clergy and prouocation of the Pope at firſt had brought in <hi>Lodouik</hi> the French kings ſonne, to be king of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in king <hi>Iohns</hi> ſteede) moued with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, falling deadly ſicke at <hi>London,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth certain of the barons vnto him &amp; ſaid: I lament your ſorowful caſe, &amp; pitie with my hart the deſtruction that is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming towards you and your country, the dangerous ſnares which are prepared for your <hi>vtter confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> are hidden vnto you: you ſee them not yet, but take heede of them <hi>in time.</hi> Prince <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douike</hi> hath ſworn no ſmaloth and ſixeteen of his Earles and Nobles with him, that if he get once the crowne, he will baniſh &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue them all of lands and goods, at leaſt, if not of life, euen as many as hee proueth to haue gone againſt their liege king and his noble perſon. And (ſaith the worthy <hi>Melune</hi>) becauſe ye ſhall not take this tale for a tale, I aſſure you on my ſoule (lying now at the mercy of God, when it is no fitte time to lie) that I was one of them which was priuy &amp; ſworne to the ſame. I haue remorſe thereof, and therefore I giue you this caueat. I pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb facs="tcp:15673:15"/>poore <hi>England,</hi> which hath bin ſo worthy a nation that now it is come to ſo miſerable extremity. And when with teares hee had blubbred a ſpace he beginneth a litle while a freſh againe: my maſters, I aduiſe you ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to prouide for future extremities <hi>in ſeaſon,</hi> I forewarn you of good will and for my conſcience ſake, and ſo after a fewe words to like ſenſe, hauing diſcharged &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burdened his heauy ſoule for the matter, he gaue vp the Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Let Engliſh harts apply this ſtory, I wil not amplifie. In the booke of <hi>Ioſua</hi> the <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bionites</hi> for all their crouchings,<note place="margin">Ioſu. 9.</note> old bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles finoed bread, and proffered friendſhip were made no better then wood-cleauers &amp; water bearers, drudges and ſlaues to the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt function. A fooliſhe &amp; a deſperate ſheaf it is that when it hath brought in fier &amp; ſette the barne all in a flame can poſſibly ſuppoſe it ſelfe can eſcape. Experience doth tell the contrary; reaſon, religion and ſcripture doe teach vs better: To wit: to forethinke our ſelues, to thinke reuerently of the Lordes annointed, &amp; to thanke God for all his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings.
<pb facs="tcp:15673:15"/>They who were weary of <hi>Salomon</hi> were wearied out with <hi>Roboam</hi> who ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded <hi>Salomon.</hi> But what ſpeak I to deaf ears, which is, but to powder the flint, to plow the rocke and ſow the ſand, and ſo to looſe both ſalt, ſeed, and labour?</p>
            <p>My brethren in chriſt, my natural and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally affected Countrimen, I ſpeake to you: we haue gods bleſſings, we finde and feele thoſe bodily and ghoſtly commodities which our poore neighbors want, God help them. Neither are our deſertes, better than theirs, for ought I ſee. Do we thinke we are priuileged without couenant of duty or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſo of forfeiting our eſtate more than are others? Security maketh fooles, and folly bringeth confuſion, and perfite wanton or waiward vnthankfullnes maketh a perfite ſeparation and diuorſe betwixt vs and our God. The noble men of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 1.</note> where they braued it moſt, and nothing remembred God, &amp; leſt thought of danger, in the hils of <hi>Gelboe</hi> loſt their liues. God forbid that the mildnes of our Queene, the fatte of our Country, the plentie of the realm, the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="tcp:15673:16"/>of our rulers, and the bleſſings of god ſhould be our bane. Nay rather God bleſſe vs with the gift of his grace in thankfulnes to bleſſe him euer that he may bleſſe vs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies more &amp; more, &amp; as <hi>Bennaiah</hi> wiſhed, ſo wiſh we al, euen god ſay ſo for euermore. The happy reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this time, the courſe of this great aſſembly, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniency of my text &amp; al holy writ beſides, iointly with this good example of the Queene of <hi>Saba</hi> &amp; the Sacrament and Euchariſt which now wee ſhal partake being y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pledge of his good wil &amp; paune of his fauor, and ſeal of his mercies to vs-ward, and likewiſe alſo on our partes to him being the prouocation and promiſe of our thankfullnes, and Sacrifice of praiſe, ſhould moue al to laude and praiſe his holy name for euer more world without end.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1. Cor. 10.15.</bibl>
                  <p>I ſpeake as vnto them which haue vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Iudge ye what I ſay.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:15673:16"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A PRAIER IN</hi> CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the former reſpects.</head>
            <p>AL humble and hartie thanks be rendred vnto thee O Lord God almightie, Father of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and compaſſion, that in this later age &amp; euil dayes, haſt placed, directed and preſerued, by thy ſinguler goodnes and ſpeciall prouidence thine handmaid ELIZABETH, our dread Soueraigne in the Seat of her father, alwaies maintaining her cauſe againſt all her enimies, who in great rage haue riſen againſt her, but thou O Lord was on her right hand, that ſhe ſhould not be moued. Continue the courſe of this thy goodnes towards vs, we beſeech thee for thy holy names ſake. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be prouoked in thy diſpleaſure for our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefulnes toward her and thee. Aſwage the malice, conuert the harts or confound the deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of al them that haue euil will to thine annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, &amp; repine at her good proceedings, &amp; ſtirre vp her hart more &amp; more to loue thee, that haſt ſo perfectly loued her, and to bleſſe thee, that ſo haſt bleſſed her, to ſerue thee her only Sauiour euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, by publiſhing peace &amp; trueth, peace, iuſtice and equitie in this church and Common wealth, that we &amp; our poſterity after vs may many yeares meet in this place and the like as at this time &amp; vpon this occaſion and to this purpoſe, that thy bleſſings O Lord may be acknowledged, our ioy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, her old age comforted, this Realme eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in the true worſhip &amp; ſeruice of thy holy name through Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
